So today’s דף daf in the בבלי Bavli is ה. Hey. We
pick up one line from the bottom on ד' עמוד ב'. Daled
Amud Bais. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. So we had a little digression
here about what do you call it, about אם למקרא aim lamikra
אם למסורת, aim lamasores, but we’ve basically been dealing with the idea
of how do you know there’s a בית דין Beis Din of
three. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. דיני ממונות בשלושה. Dinei mamonos b'shlosha. אם
היה מומחה לרבים. Im hayah mumche l'rabbim. So look at this, the
last thing we just did in the בבלי Bavli in the ירושלמי
Yerushalmi now is ירושלמי Yerushalmi in the בבלי. Bavli. Is however the
person was an expert for the community דן אפילו יחידי. dan afilu
yechidi.
Now you're authorized to judge even alone, exactly the thing we left
off in the בבלי. Bavli. You can judge even alone. Now what
is this definition of מומחה לרבים? mumche l'rabbim? אמר רב נחמן Amar
Rav Nachman כגון אנא דן דיני ממונות ביחידי, kigon ana dan dinei
mamonos b'yechidi,
like I would be a good example of a מומחה לרבים mumche
l'rabbim and I could judge even by myself. וכן אמר רבי חייא
V'chein amar Rabbi Chiya כגון אנא דן דיני ממונות ביחידי. kigon ana
dan dinei mamonos b'yechidi. And רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya said the same
thing. Now איבעיא להו, ibayalu, we wanted to know what constitutes מומחה
לרבים? mumche l'rabbim? כגון אנא דגמירנא וסבירנא, kigon ana digmurna v'savirna,
like I that I have learned and so גמירנא gmurna means that
I've learned the traditions, I'm erudite, okay we would say, and סבירנא
savirna means I have good analysis. I'm both erudite and I've received
all the received traditions and I also know how to make judgments
and analyze and think things through. So is that what you need,
so you've passed all your law exams, that's one level.
And number two, ונקטינא רשותא, v'naktna rishusa, I also have been licensed,
I'm trying to translate into contemporary terms. I've gotten permission from the
political Jewish political head to judge. Is that part of what you
need? אבל לא נקטי רשותא דיניה לא דינא, Aval lo nakt rishusa
dinei lo dina, but without that licensing, without that permission, the judgment
is not binding. עוד דילמא אף על גב דלא נקטי רשותא דיניה
דינא, Od dilma af al gav d'lo nakt rishusa dinei dina, or
no, maybe if you know the law and you're a תלמיד חכם
talmid chacham and whatever, you don't need permission and it is binding.
So this is the question about a דיין יחידי. dayan yechidi. Now
I just want to pause for a moment and say how did
we get to דיין יחידי? dayan yechidi? We said you needed three.
It is true that the גמרא Gemara before quoted an opinion that
said בצדק תשפוט עמיתך b'tzedek tishpot amisecha that when it comes to
הודאות והלוואות, hodaos v'halvaos, you don't need three, one is enough and
so on.
But the question is is that is this working within this, cause
this has a demand of מומחה לרבים. mumche l'rabbim. And pretty much
the position of the ראשונים Rishonim is that this is even if
you say in principle from the תורה's Torah perspective you need three
even for הודאות והלוואות hodaos v'halvaos for all דיני ממונות, dinei mamonos,
rabbinically we allowed there to be a דיין יחידי, dayan yechidi, a
single judge, as long as he was a מומחה לרבים mumche l'rabbim
for the same reasons we've been discussing before, לא תנעול דלת בפני
לווין, lo tinol deles bifnei lovin, to make monetary cases easier to
handle. So the basic point is that most understand that this idea
of מומחה לרבים mumche l'rabbim is like a rabbinic institution. Maybe it's
true דאורייתא d'oraisa you need three, we're going to allow there to
be a single judge but not any joker, not any יושבי קרנות,
yoshvei kranos, he's got to be somebody that really knows his stuff.
And if you understand that that's the way it is, it's like
this rabbinic institution, you also understand the idea of ונקטינא רשותא, v'naktna
rishusa, right? From some תורה Torah הלכה halachic perspective, why, what's this
idea of getting some
licensing? But if the רבנים Rabbis said we're going to allow individual
judges if they really know their stuff, they might also have said
and if they've been licensed to do it, if they've been given
that permission. So therefore we're going to give them that power. Now
I want to say one other important thing about this idea of
מומחה לרבים mumche l'rabbim because מומחה mumche is sometimes used, if you
remember רש"י Rashi back on ב' עמוד ב', Bais Amud Bais, said
מומחה mumche meant, רש"י Rashi said סמיכה, smicha, which means the authority
going all the way back to משה רבינו. Moshe Rabbeinu. That is
when we have to satisfy the word אלוהים Elohim in the פסוק.
pasuk. אלוהים Elohim means representing God, so it has to be some
authority that goes all the way back to הר סיני, Har Sinai,
all the way back to משה רבינו. Moshe Rabbeinu. That's normally a
type of authority that's needed, for example to judge דיני קנסות, dinei
knasos, to impose monetary signs, certainly to impose מלקות malkus or execution.
There you need סמיכה smicha going back to משה. Moshe. And that's
one way the word מומחה mumche is used. As you'll notice that
is not the way it's used here, there's no mention of סמיכה.
smicha. It says you know your stuff and you've been licensed. So
רמב"ן Ramban is brilliant. רמב"ן Ramban says the key difference to know,
other than context, of whether we're referring to מומחה mumche meaning סמיכה
smicha or מומחה mumche in this context is the word, the difference
between מומחה mumche and מומחה לרבים. mumche l'rabbim. Now for you and
me, the word מומחה לרבים mumche l'rabbim sounds like it's a higher
level. It's not enough that you're a מומחה, mumche, it has to
be for the masses. But the רמב"ן Ramban says no, it means
you're recognized by the community for your expertise, but you're not an
expert in objective terms.
Somebody that's, so the community acknowledges your expertise, but it's not like
we, the מומחה mumche in objective terms is a specific status of
being of סמיכה smicha going back to משה רבינו. Moshe Rabbeinu. Okay,
so he says מומחה. mumche. Actually is a lower status than מומחה.
Mumche. It means from the community's perspective they see your expertise. I'll
actually read you the phrase: ופירוש מומחה לרבים, Upeirash Mumche Larabbim, this
is the Ramban, בדוק להם. baduk lahem.
It means that you have been tested by them. They have had
experience with you and they accept you. כעניין שאמרו בקמיע מן המומחה.
Ke'inyan she'amru bekamei'a min hamumche. So when they said to say if
you have a קמיע, kamei'a, you know an amulet written from a
מומחה, mumche, a מומחה mumche means somebody that the community has come
to rely on for writing these קמיעות. kameiot. Okay, שהכל יודעים בו
דגמיר וסביר. Shehakol yodim bo degamir vesavir.
Everybody knows that he's a smart guy. וקראו מומחה לרבים משום דמומחה
להם. Vekaro mumche larabbim mishum demumche lahem. He's מומחה להם mumche lahem
ואינו מומחה לתורה, ve'eino mumche latorah, but he's not necessarily from the
Torah perspective a מומחה mumche שאינו סמוך ברבי. she'eino samuch berabbi. He
doesn't have the סמיכה smicha that allows him to be called Rabbi,
you know, the סמיכה smicha from משה רבנו. Moshe Rabbeinu. Okay, but
that's important to know that there are two usages of the term
מומחה. mumche. So this is the one that has is a תלמיד
חכם talmid chacham recognized by the רבים, rabbim, maybe has a licensing,
and that person is entitled to judge even by himself, even without
a בית דין beit din of three.
So the גמרא Gemara wants to say but what if he doesn't
have licensing? So תא שמע, Ta shema, come in here. מר זוטרא
בריה דרב נחמן דן דינא. Mar Zutra bereih d'Rav Nachman dan dina.
מר זוטרא Mar Zutra the son of רב נחמן Rav Nachman made
a judgment, and we somehow assume that this was somebody that did
not have licensing from the like ריש גלותא. Reish Galuta. Okay, so
he- he- he gave a ruling, דן דינא, dan dina, וטעה, veta'ah,
and he made an error. אתא לקמיה דרב יוסף Ata lekamei d'Rav
Yosef and came to רב יוסף. Rav Yosef. אמר ליה, Amar leih,
רב יוסף Rav Yosef said, אם קיבלוך עלייהו, Im kibluch aleiyhu, here
again notice the parallel to the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, if they accepted your
authority, לא תשלם, lo tishaleim, you don't have to pay. Okay, they
accepted your authority and like we've seen in the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, that
gives you more latitude, that means sort of like whatever you judge
is going to be okay. So you don't have to pay. ואי
לא, Ve'ee lo, but if they didn't accept your authority and you
imposed your authority on them, זיל שלים, zil shaleim, go pay. Now
for us, right, that's interesting in the question about what do you
call it? About- about malpractice or whatever, you know, so if they
accept your authority obviously then pretty much everything you say is binding,
right, that's sort of what we've seen. If you impose your authority
it has to more match up to some objective standard and there
could be a case where you're going to have to pay. But
for us what's important is not that, but that even if they
didn't accept his authority, the judgment stood. Forget what he has to
pay. The judgment stood. So that- and we somehow know that it's
a case that he was not נקט רשותא, nakat reshuta, he didn't
have licensing. So you see that מומחה לרבים mumche larabbim suffices. Here's
a case where it's not just stam they accepted him, he imposed
his authority, and nevertheless the- forgetting paying, the judgment stood. Okay, and
therefore that's the proof that even without licensing it would still be
a valid judgment. Okay, שמע מינה, Shma mina, from this you can
infer, כי לא נקט רשותא דינא דינא, ki lo nakat reshuta dina
dina, even without the licensing which is as apparently was the case,
the judgment was still a judgment. Even imposed judgment was still a
judgment. שמע מינה, Shma mina, that's a good proof. Okay, now אמר
רב, Amar Rav, said
רב, Rav, האי מאן דבעי למידין דינא, hai man deba'i lemidein dina,
אי טעי בעי למיפטרא. ee ta'ei ba'ei lemiftera. Now if you want
to judge and you want to actually get out of having to
pay, okay, so the ירושלמי Yerushalmi would have said, you know what
you do? If you want to get out of having to pay,
you get them to- to willingly accept your authority. Okay, but let's
say you want to impose your authority or let's say that whatever,
and you still want to get out of paying. Okay, here's what
you do. So, לישקול רשותא מבי ריש גלותא. Lishkol reshuta mibei Reish
Galuta. Take- get authority, get licensing. The licensing will exempt you from
having to pay. So you might not need the licensing to have
your judgments binding, right? מומחה לרבים Mumche larabbim is enough to have
your judgments binding and maybe even you can impose your authority as
a מומחה לרבים, mumche larabbim, which is pretty interesting, right? Because who's
going to decide whether you're a מומחה לרבים mumche larabbim or not?
Who- who identifies you as such? Okay, but as a מומחה לרבים
mumche larabbim your judgments are binding, but if you want to be
exempt from- from liability for your judgments, you have to get- get
your licensing from the ריש גלותא. Reish Galuta. וכן אמר שמואל, Vechen
amar Shmuel, and שמואל Shmuel says the same thing, לישקול רשותא מבי
ריש גלותא. lishkol reshuta mibei Reish Galuta. You get your רשות. reshut.
So that might not be necessary for it to be a דין,
din, but it is necessary to exempt you from payment.
Now can he- even once your judgment has been challenged, like in
the process that you made a judgment-
Oh you mean if you keep on making mistakes, if you keep
on making mistakes I assume the ריש גלותא Reish Galuta can retract
his- his licensing. So it's a good question, right, but you know
but obviously we're all human and we all make mistakes.
Well, I guess I'm asking I don't exactly understand how the appeal
process works here.
Oh, that's an excellent point too. Who decides that you made a
mistake? Like we're talking about if you made a mistake do you
have to pay, who gets to decide you did make a mistake?
That's a real good question. So we're going to get to the
more questions of mistakes and paying tomorrow, so let's try to revisit
that then. But that's an excellent question. Okay, so גמרא Gemara says
like this. Now
פשיטא, peshita, now that we're dealing with this issue of giving רשות,
rishus, where it either means that that gives it authority to be
binding, or if not necessarily to be binding, but at least authority
gives you the weight of the government or the authority behind you
so you don't have to pay if it's judged that you made
a mistake, we want to discuss the scope of that רשות. rishus.
So it says like this: פשיטא מהכא להכא, Peshita me-hacha le-hacha, if
somebody was given that authority here in בבל Bavel and they're judging
here in בבל, Bavel, ומהתם להתם, u-me-hasam le-hasam, and from there for
there, if they were given the authority to be in ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael to judge in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, I'll read it
with the parentheses, מהני, mahani, obviously that authority would work, that granting
of authority. Okay. ומהכא להתם, U-me-hacha le-hasam, now, if they were given
authority here in בבל Bavel to judge in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael,
נמי מהני, nami mahani, that would also work. Why? Okay, we'll see
in a minute. Because דהכא שבט והתם מחוקק. de-hacha shevet ve-hasam mechokek.
Here we have the staff and there's just the lawgiver. What does
that mean? כדתניא: Ke-detanya:
לא יסור שבט מיהודה, Lo yasur shevet mi-Yehuda, the staff should never
be removed from Judah. אלו ראשי גלויות שבבבל, Elu Roshei Galuyos she-be-Bavel,
these are the heads of the of the, you know, of the
exile, the political heads, ריש גלותא Reish Galusa in בבל. Bavel. Now
why is that a שבט, shevet, a staff, which is like, you
know, carry a big stick? שרודין את ישראל בשבט, She-rodin es Yisrael
be-shevet,
because they actually have like the power of, you know, we have
all these stories of the ריש גלותא Reish Galusa house and they
don't like what certain rabbis are doing and they throw them in
jail and you know, and whatever, so they had some actual, you
know, army behind, not army, I don't know, but anyway, police force
behind them, the government gave them some actual power to compel with
force. Okay, so they actually have that staff.
ומחוקק מבין רגליו, U-mechokek mi-bein raglav, and the lawgiver from from his
loins. אלו בני בניו של הלל, Elu benei banav shel Hillel, these
are the descendants of Hillel שמלמדים תורה ברבים. she-melamdim Torah be-rabbim. They
teach Torah, they're lawgivers. They teach Torah. So even right it was
very interesting, we always know about like רב יהודה הנשיא, Reb Yehuda
HaNasi, right? And we know רב יהודה הנשיא Reb Yehuda HaNasi was
a נשיא, Nasi, he was a political head. But mostly we think
of him as a big Rabbi, right? Because, you know, because basically
they had the combination of the political authority and the rabbinic authority
were combined in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael to the House of רבי.
Rebbi. In בבל Bavel they were separate. ריש גלותא Reish Galusa was
political authority and there was no single like, you know, rabbinic authority.
But what the גמרא Gemara is pointing out is it's all very
nice to have those two combined, but it also meant that he
was not so much of a, you know, he didn't have so
much, you know, physical strength, not physical strength, that's not the word,
whatever, you know, power, you know, political power behind his rulings. He
couldn't go ahead and call out the troops if people weren't listening
to him. It was probably more by acclaim and by persuasion and
so on. So therefore, you know, he's a lawgiver. What does רבי
Rebbi do? You know what רבי Rebbi and Hillel and their descendants
do? They teach Torah. It's not like they actually send out the
troops. They teach Torah ברבים. be-rabbim. Okay, that's what, just. Just, just
teach Torah. They teach Torah. They're מחוקק מבין רגליו, mechokek mi-bein raglav,
מלמדים תורה ברבים. melamdim Torah be-rabbim. I also wonder by the way
if there was a little bit of a point because all of
this is about the ascent, the power of בבל, Bavel, if there's
a little bit of a dig here because Hillel was Babylonian. It's
הלל הבבלי. Hillel HaBavli. So even the authority of Torah that they
have going on in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael ultimately derives from בבל.
Bavel. But anyway, but so there they have it's great that they
have the House of the נשיא, Nasi, but they're basically Torah teachers.
Okay, and therefore this issue, and here's why it's relevant, now that
we're dealing with סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, we're not just dealing with abstract Torah
law. We're talking about imposed authority, right? So the idea that there
is a power behind it and it's binding, so it actually says
if they got that power in בבל, Bavel, that's binding in ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael because that's a power that has behind it some
real like, you know, the staff, some real power, some real bindingness
to it. Okay, of course the funny thing is since when does
בבל Bavel have authority in ארץ ישראל? Eretz Yisrael? Might be very
nice the ריש גלותא Reish Galusa power in בבל. Bavel. That doesn't
extend to ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. So it's still not exactly clear
why they cross borders. Okay, but it sort of saying that since
this is about giving the bindingness and the backing to the ruling,
either to make it binding or that you don't have to pay,
clearly from בבל Bavel it works to ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. But
here's the question: ומהתם
להכא מאי? U-me-hasam le-hacha mai? How about if they got authority in
ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, what would be the relevance of that for
rulings that they gave in בבל? Bavel? תא שמע, Ta shema, coming
here. דרבה בר חנה, De-Rabbah bar Chana, רבה בר חנה Rabbah bar
Chana who we're going to find out in a story was given
authority through from רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael.
Okay, so he got his authority in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Now
actually the... Part of the point is of the phrase מהכא להתם
me-hacha le-hatam
or מהתם להכא me-hatam le-hacha doesn't just mean they were authorized in
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and then they traveled to בבל. Bavel. What
it means is they were authorized in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael for
the purpose of ruling in בבל. Bavel. So it was actually done
with that in mind, and we still want to know should we
have to listen to the authority that they granted this guy in
ארץ ישראל? Eretz Yisrael? This guy was traveling to בבל, Bavel, he
got authority in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael to פסקן pasken in בבל.
Bavel. Why should that be relevant to us? Okay, that's the question.
So we're going to find the story that רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya
was given authority before he left ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael to פסקן
pasken in בבל Bavel to be a דיין. dayan. אמר ליה, Amar
lei, so וטעה, ve-ta'ah, now he made a mistake, ואתא לקמיה דרבי
חייא, ve-ata le-kamei de-Rabbi Chiya, he went back to רבי חייא Rabbi
Chiya who was in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, who was the one
who we're going to find out gave him his authority. אמר ליה,
Amar lei, and he said, אי קיבלוך עלייהו לא תשלם, Ei kibluch
alayhu lo teshalem, if they accepted your authority, don't pay. ואי לא
זיל שלים, ve-ei lo zil shelim, and if not, go pay. So
והא רבה בר חנה, ve-ha Rabba bar Chana, and presumably we know
that the case was that he judged this case in בבל. Bavel.
והא רבה בר חנה רשותא הוה נקיט, ve-ha Rabba bar Chana reshuta
hava nakit, but actually he was given authority from רבי חייא Rabbi
Chiya himself who gave him this ruling. So שמע מינה, Shema mina,
so why does he have to pay? If he's been given that
backing, then he should be exempt. שמע מינה מהתם להכא לא מהני,
Shema mina me-hatam le-hacha lo mahani, that authority given in ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael to rule in בבל Bavel does not help them, doesn't
make it, whether it's binding or not, maybe you don't even need
the רשות reshut to be binding, but it doesn't get them out
of the obligation to pay if they make a mistake. שמע מינה,
Shema mina, that's a good proof. Then the גמרא Gemara says one
minute, ולא מהני, ve-lo mahani, is that really true that it doesn't
work? והא רבה בר רב הונא, ve-ha Rabba bar Rav Huna, this
is not the same, before it was רבה בר חנה, Rabba bar
Chana, here it's רבה בר רב הונא. Rabba bar Rav Huna. כי
הוה מנצי בהדי דבי ריש גלותא, Ki hava mantzi bahadi de-bei Resh
Galuta, when he would fight with the house of the ריש גלותא,
Resh Galuta, אמר, amar, he would say to them, like he would
give a פסק psak they wouldn't like, he would say to them,
לאו מינייכו נקיטנא רשותא, lav minaichu nakitna reshuta, hey, don't think that
my authority derives from you, which it should therefore if he's in
בבל. Bavel. נקיטנא רשותא מאבא מרי, Nakitna reshuta mi-Abba Mari, I have
my authority
to פסקן pasken from אבא מרי, Abba Mari, ואבא מרי מרב ורב
מרבי חייא ורבי חייא מרבי. ve-Abba Mari mi-Rav ve-Rav mi-Rabbi Chiya ve-Rabbi
Chiya mi-Rebbi. I have my authority going all the way back to
רבי יהודה הנשי. Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi. So his defense against the ריש
גלותא Resh Galuta is that his authority derives from ארץ ישראל, Eretz
Yisrael, right? So that sounds like ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael authority has
some weight in בבל. Bavel. So the גמרא Gemara says, so what's
the גמרא's Gemara answer? So the גמרא's Gemara answer
is במילתא דעלמא הוא דאוקים להו. be-milta d'alma hu d'okim le-hu. Nah,
he was just trying to get them off his back. What he
was saying wasn't really true. His authority from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael
really had no meaning in בבל, Bavel, but he was just dropping
names in order to get them to stop giving him a hard
time, but it did not really have legal binding. Of course, it's
very interesting, one wonders, we haven't dealt with this in the ירושלמי,
Yerushalmi, but one wonders what the ירושלמי's Yerushalmi view of this would
be. From the בבלי's Bavli perspective, ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael authority doesn't
really mean anything in בבל, Bavel, but בבל's Bavel authority means something
in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. One wonders if they would have had
a different view of these things in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Okay,
but now that's the גמרא's Gemara conclusion, that it does not work
in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael for בבל. Bavel. Now the גמרא Gemara
says like this, וכי מאחר דלא מהני, ve-chi me-achar de-lo mahani, now
one minute, if the authority from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael to בבל
Bavel is not helpful, רבה בר חנה רשותא נקט למה לי, Rabba
bar Chana reshuta nakat lama li, so then why did he have
to get authority? If he was
going to בבל, Bavel, what was the point of that authority?
לאייותי עומדים על הגבולין. Le-ayoti omdim al ha-gevulin. Ah, he needed it
because there were some towns that had overlapping authority between, overlapping, whether
they were under the ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael control or the בבל
Bavel control. So he would at least be able to פסקן pasken
in those regions because of the authority and with exemption from
payment because of the authority he got from ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael.
But when you're in the heartland of בבל, Bavel, your authority will
not help you. Again, the judgments might be binding, but you are
not exempt from liability if you judged incorrectly. So now the גמרא
Gemara says like this, now we're going to get to the story
of how he got his authority and you will see the source
of a phrase that is extremely familiar to you. כי הוה נחית
רבה בר חנה לבבל, Ki hava nachit Rabba bar Chana le-Bavel, now
when רבה בר חנה Rabba bar Chana was going to בבל, Bavel,
this is the background story to what we were saying
before, אמר ליה רבי חייא לרבי, amar lei Rabbi Chiya le-Rebbi, so
רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya said to רבי, Rebbi, right, רבי חייא, Rabbi
Chiya, he said, בן אחי יורד לבבל, ben achi yored le-Bavel, my
nephew, the son of my brother, is going to בבל. Bavel. Notice
the word יורד, yored, going down to בבל. Bavel. יורה? Yoreh? Does
he have the authority to פסקן? pasken? יורה. Yoreh. He has, so
יורה יורה Yoreh Yoreh is a question and an answer. Does he
have the authority to פסקן pasken in matters of like איסור והיתר,
issur ve-hetter, that's what הוראה hora'ah means? Yes, he has that authority.
ידין? Yadin? Does he have the authority to judge דיני ממונות? dinei
mamonot? ידין, Yadin, he has that authority. So ידין ידין Yadin Yadin
is the authority of דיני ממונות, dinei mamonot, okay. יתיר בכורות? Yatir
bechorot? Does he have the authority to look at blemishes on firstborn?
on animals to determine whether it's a genuine blemish and therefore the
animal does not have to be brought as a קרבן korban and
he can't bring it as a קרבן. korban. The only way you
could eat a בכור bechor nowadays is if it had a blemish.
So does he have the authority to rule on blemishes? יתיר בכורות.
yattir bechorot. Yes, he has that authority. Nobody nowadays is getting יתיר
בכורות, יתיר בכורות. yattir bechorot, yattir bechorot. I don't know why. Anyway.
Okay, so that was that authority. Now, כי הא דנחית רב לבבל,
ki ha denachit Rav leVavel, now that was רבה בר חנה. Rabba
bar Chana. When רב Rav was going to בבל, Bavel, who was
also a nephew of רבי חייא, Rabbi Chiyya, so אמר ליה רבי
חייא לרבי, amar lei Rabbi Chiyya leRabbi, רבי חייא Rabbi Chiyya said
to רבי, Rabbi, בן אחותי יורד לבבל, ben achoti yored leVavel, my
sister's son is going to בבל. Bavel. יורה, yoreh, can he פסקן
pasken in איסור והיתר? issur veheter? יורה. yoreh. ידין, yadin, can he
פסקן pasken in דיני ממונות? dinei mamonot? ידין. yadin. יתיר בכורות, yattir
bechorot, can he be מתיר בכורות? matir bechorot? אל יתיר. al yattir.
He can't. Okay. Now we have some, before we figure out why
you needed the authority, given what we've just been saying, we first
want to unpack this case. So first of all, מאי שנא למר
דקקרי בן אחי ומאי שנא למר דקקרי בן אחותי? mai shena lemar
dekakari ben achi u'mai shena lemar dekakari ben achoti? Why does he
call רבה בר בר חנה Rabba bar bar Chana his brother's son
and רב Rav his sister's son? Now the answer is, well, maybe
that's what they were. וכי תימא הכי הוה מעשה? vechi teima hachi
hava ma'aseh? That was the case, one was his brother's son, one
was his sister's son. The גמרא Gemara says no, it's not true,
they were both sons of brothers of his.
והאמר מר איבו וחנא ושילא ומרתא ורבי חייא כולהו בני אבא בר
אחא כרסלא מכפרי הוו. ve'ha'amar mar Aivo veChana veShila veMarta veRabbi Chiyya
kulhu bnei Abba bar Acha Carsela miKafri havu. They were all the
sons of this one man. They were all brothers. So רבי חייא,
Rabbi Chiyya, one of his brothers was חנא, Chana, so רבה בר
חנה, Rabba bar Chana, and I know it sounds like a woman's
name but it was a man's name, רבה בר חנה Rabba bar
Chana was his brother's son. But the other brother here was איבו,
Aivo, and איבו Aivo was רב's Rav father. So both רב Rav
and רבה בר חנה Rabba bar Chana were sons of his brothers,
different brothers. So why did he call רב Rav his sister's son
when רב Rav was really his brother's son? Okay. So the גמרא
Gemara says, רב בר אחוה דהוה בר אחתיה, Rav bar achuha d'hava
bar achatei, because no, so the answer was רב Rav was both
his sister's son and his brother's son. רב Rav was married to
a half sister and a half brother who weren't related to one
another. You can figure it out. But anyway, the first answer is
רב Rav was truly רב Rav was his brother's son but also
his sister's son. רב בר אחוה דהוה בר אחתיה. Rav bar achuha
d'hava bar achatei. רבה בר חנה בר אחוה דלאו בר אחתיה, Rabba
bar Chana bar achuha delav bar achatei, and רבה בר חנה Rabba
bar Chana was only a brother's son. ואיבעית אימא, ve'iba'it eima, and
if you want I'll tell you, על שם חכמתו, al shem chochmato,
that he called רב Rav his sister's son because רב Rav was
really smarter. דכתיב אמור לחכמה אחותי את, dechtiv emor lachochmah achoti at,
say to wisdom, you are my sister. So by saying sister's son,
it was a nice poetic way of saying he's a big תלמיד
חכם, talmid chacham, he has real חכמה. chochmah. But of course now
that just raises the question: why was רב Rav not given the
same authority? רב Rav wasn't given the authority to be מתיר בכורות.
matir bechorot. So the גמרא Gemara says, יתיר בכורות אל יתיר. yattir
bechorot al yattir. One minute. So now that we said that רב
Rav wasn't given authority to מתיר בכורות, matir bechorot, מאי טעמא? mai
ta'ama? Why? אילימא משום דלא חכים, eilima mishum d'lo chakim, he wasn't
so
smart? הא קאמרת דחכים טפי, ha ka'amart dechakim tefei, you just said
that he was smarter, that's why he called him the son of
my sister.
Number one. אלא משום דלא בקי במומין, ela mishum d'lo baki be'mumin,
so you'll say, okay, it's one thing being book smart, it's another
thing knowing facts. Maybe he just didn't have the experience to know
what to look for when he was looking at blemishes. So the
גמרא Gemara says no, והאמר רב, ve'ha'amar Rav, רב Rav said, שמונה
עשר חדשים גדלתי אצל רועה בהמה, shmonah asar chodashim gadalti etzel ro'eh
behemah, I went and I did an apprenticeship for eighteen months with
shepherds, לידע איזה מום קבוע ואיזה מום עובר, leida eizeh mum kavua
v'eizeh mum over, what was a permanent blemish and a non-permanent blemish.
So he knew his stuff. He knew it in the books, he
knew it in practice. Why was he not given this authority? So
the גמרא Gemara says, אלא לחלק לו כבוד לרבה בר חנה, ela
lachaloik lo kavod leRabba bar Chana, because they wanted רבה בר חנה
Rabba bar Chana to make sure people gave him a lot of
respect. As רש"י Rashi said, רב Rav didn't need this to get
respect. Because רב Rav was the bigger authority, it actually, he was
okay not having official right to פסקן pasken in בכור. bechor. He
would have gotten plenty of respect without that. But by giving רבה
בר חנה Rabba bar Chana a certain authority that רב Rav didn't
have, it ensured that רבה בר חנה Rabba bar Chana would get
sufficient respect. Very interesting. Okay. ואיבעית אימא, ve'iba'it eima, and if you
want I'll tell you, משום הא גופא. mishum ha gufa. Because רב
Rav was so knowledgeable, that's why he wasn't given the authority. Huh?
דרב בקי במומין טפי, de'Rav baki be'mumin tefei,
he was so expert in the blemishes, דשרי מומין דלא ידעי אינשי.
de'sharei mumin d'lo yad'ei inshi. He'll permit a blemish that in, from
most people's perspective, looks like it wasn't a blemish. So from most
people's perspective, it'll look like he's doing the wrong thing. Sometimes you
could be too smart for your own good. Okay. ואמרי, v'amri, and
people will say, כי האי גוונא שרא רב, ki hai gavna shara
Rav, and they'll say, oh, well if רב Rav allowed a בכור
bechor like this, then this also has to be allowed. But they
won't be able to discern why one was okay and one wasn't
okay. ואתו למישרי מום עובר, v'atu lemishrei mum over, and they'll come
to permit a passing blemish. Okay. So that was interesting in terms
of those differences. But now we still have to get back to
the question, א, A, we're going to look at יורה יורה, yoreh
yoreh, which is of course what our classic סמיכה smicha is, and
we're going to have to get back to the question of why.
Why did he need authority? What good was the authority if it
didn't exempt him from payment, right? Which was our question to begin
with. But first, let's look at יורה יורה. Yoreh Yoreh. So יורה
יורה, Yoreh Yoreh, אי גמיר רשותא למה לי למשקל? i gamir reshusa
lama li lemishkal? So if אי גמיר, i gamir, if the guy's
a תלמיד חכם, talmid chacham, רשותא למה לי למשקל? reshusa lama li
lemishkal? Why do you need to get authority? Meaning it's one thing
we were talking about authority to judge דיני ממונות. dinei mammonos. That
might be necessary if I want to compel you to come to
court, or it might be necessary to exempt me if I rule
incorrectly. But if you're giving me authority to פסקן pasken on כשרות
kashrus or שבת, Shabbos, I'm not going to force you to come
to me. If you come to me, I'll give you a פסק.
psak. Why do I need the licensing for that? Right? And where,
you know, there's no issue about paying for a mistake, there's no
issue of compelling authority. It's all you just decide to come to
me. So who needs licensing for that? Good question. אי גמיר, i
gamir, if you know your הלכה, halacha, רשותא למה לי למשקל? reshusa
lama li lemishkal? Why do you need to be licensed? משום מעשה
שהיה, mishum maaseh shehayah, because of the following
story. דתניא, detanya, we taught in a ברייתא, braisa, פעם אחת הלך
רבי למקום אחד, Paam achas halach Rebbe lemakom echad, רבי Rebbe went
to a certain
place. וראה בני אדם שמגבלין עיסותיהם בטומאה, vera bnei adam shemagvilin isoseihem
betuma, and he saw that people were kneading their dough, עיסותיהם, isoseihem,
and they were טמא, tamei, and they weren't concerned that they were
making their dough טמא. tamei. אמר להם, amar lahem, מפני מה אתם
מגבלין עיסותיכם בטומאה? mipnei mah atem megvilin isoseichem betuma? Why are you
doing this? אמרו לו, amru lo, they said to him, תלמיד אחד
בא לכאן, talmid echad ba l'chan, because there was a sage that
once came here or תלמיד, talmid, והורה לנו, vehoreh lanu, מי בצעים
אין מכשירין, mei bitzaim ein machshirin, and he told us water from
like ditches does not make the food susceptible to becoming טמא. tamei.
You know food has to come in contact with a liquid. So
therefore, we're using normal well water or ditch water, whatever, and based
on his פסק, psak, it's not a problem. And they misheard him.
והוא, vehu, this person, this רב rav who פסקן-ed pasken for them,
מי ביצים דרש להו, mei beitzim darash lehu, he said if you
use eggs, if you're making egg חלה challah with no water, it
won't be טמא. tamei. So he had the word מי ביצים mei
beitzim and he didn't pronounce it well, or and they heard him
say מי בצעים, mei bitzaim, which was like ditch water. Okay, so
what shows you it's not enough to know הלכה, halacha, you have
to know how to talk to people, okay? And you have to
know like, you know, what it means to be a רב rav
in practice. Okay, ואינהו סברי, ve'innu savri, and they thought מי בצעים
קאמר, mei bitzaim ka'amar, ותנא נמי בהא, vetana nami beha, and another
mistake: מי תרמיון ומי פיגה פסולין מפני שהן מי בצעים mei Tirmion
u'mei Pigah psulin mipnei shehein mei bitzaim or whatever or מי ביצים
mei beitzim or whatever. You know, that these waters from certain rivers
are invalid to use for פרה אדומה parah adumah water because they're
like muddy
waters, okay? It's like ditch water, okay? And so it's not מים
חיים mayim chayim to use for פרה אדומה. parah adumah. ואינהו סברי,
ve'innu savri, and they thought, מדלגבי חטאת פסולי, mideilgabei chatas psuli,
since you can't use that water for, you know, the ashes of
the פרה אדומה, parah adumah, אכשורי נמי לא מכשירי, achshurei nami lo
machshiri, it doesn't count as water for anything and it's not a
problem for susceptibility for טומאה. tumah. ולא היא, velo hi, and obviously
that's not true. התם לענין חטאת בעינן מים חיים, hasam l'inyan chatas
ba'inan mayim chayim, there you needed live water, clean water from a
well, הכא אכשורי, hacha achshurei, when it comes to making food susceptible,
כל דהו מכשיר, kol d'hu machshir,
anything can. Anyway, that was completely parenthetical because that's just... the real
point is the רב rav פסקן-ed pasken for them and he wasn't
careful for how his words were being heard. Okay, which shows it's
not enough to be a תלמיד חכם, talmid chacham, you know, you
have to know how to be responsible when dealing with people. תניא,
tanya, and we taught in a ברייתא, braisa, באותה שעה, be'osah sha'ah,
at that moment, גזרו, gazru, תלמיד אל יורה אלא אם כן נוטל
רשותא מרבו. talmid al yoreh ela im kein notal reshusa mei-rabbah. So
here was the first licensing of a profession. Until now, we dealt
with licensing that you have to have like the police force behind
you if you want to compel somebody to come to court for
דיני ממונות. dinei mammonos. Or you need the licensing to tell me,
"Hey, I'm exempt from liability, I have a special license from the
government." Here we're talking about the standard licensing to essentially ensure that
you don't have irresponsible people doing the job. Even though פסקן-ing pasken
a הלכה halacha שאלה shaila is not a question of compelling and
it's not a question about payment or whatever for, you know, for
malpractice, people should not accept a רב rav as an authority for
their community unless he has received a license from his רבי Rebbe
because there's a responsibility here and we're not, you know, and you
need to know that somebody like the—you know, it's like why—you know,
the whole idea of a licensing is the members of the profession
give a license. I could go to a guy and hey, he
sounds like he really knows his stuff, sounds like he's a good
doctor, you know, but obviously I'm being irresponsible with my own health.
You need to know from the members of the profession. So somebody
needs to get a license from his רבי, Rebbe, and we are
telling everybody else you should not accept him as a רב rav
unless he's received that licensing. Okay, so this is the basis why
יורה יורה Yoreh Yoreh becomes—we don't have סמיכה semicha obviously going back
to משה רבינו, Moshe Rabbeinu, but now you understand why the phrase
יורה יורה Yoreh Yoreh became the way in which the community was
told that rabbis were licensed and they could trust them. trust a
rabbi and their
פסק, Pesak, and this was how rabbinic licensing came up, and the
phrase יורה יורה Yoreh Yoreh was used as a way of saying
you can trust this guy, he's a responsible rabbi. Okay, and that's
so it doesn't really satisfy a הלכה halakhic requirement. It satisfies like
a communal requirement and the need for licensing. All right, so we're
going to end here but what we still going to have to
get back to is the question about why you needed the authority
for ידין ידין Yadin Yadin if he was anyway going to be
exempt from if it didn't help in בבל? Bavel? Because we still
haven't answered that question. What good was that authority if it didn't
help in בבל Bavel for דיני ממונות? dinei mamonot? But we'll return
to that tomorrow.